The sound of a train running alongside a river
The color of sunflowers blooming facing down
The sunset becomes a striped border
Why do I want to cry every time you say "thank you"?
I'm like a child
I thought I'd left all my tears in the fridge
Red rover, red rover, send that girl right over
Goodbye, bystander
We keep walking
Even if at the end of this road isn't Heaven or anything like that
I just want to keep being with you and smiling together
Pride, wishes, and hope
I'll always have them just like you do
When you're scared, so scared, and becoming depressed
I'll protect you, I'll always protect you with everything I have
I promise you to your face
New School Year
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）
そんな気がしていたけれど—
I knew this would happen,
Class 2-B
but because of us changing classes for the new school year,
Mr. Hayashida was no longer my homeroom teacher.
２年になるクラス替えで—
林田先生とは クラスが別れた
Um, lunch...
（零）えーと 昼ごはん…
（男子生徒Ａ）急げ！
Hurry!
They'll sell out of the double minced meat sandwich!
ビッグダブルメンチサンド
売り切れちまう！
（男子生徒Ｂ）負けねぇ 俺は
から揚げポテトサラダのサンドだ！
Whatever! I'm getting the fried chicken potato salad sandwich!
The ball is your friend! I'm prepared to shock the world!
（男子生徒Ｃ）ボールは友達
（男子生徒Ｄ）
世界を驚かす覚悟がある
Hey, is it true he's a year older?
（女子生徒Ａ）ねぇ
あの人 １個上って本当？
So he's repeating a year? Why?
Dazed
（女子生徒Ｂ）えー ダブってんだ
何で？
I heard he plays shogi or something. I'm not sure.
（女子生徒Ｃ）
何か 将棋とかやってんだって
よく分かんないけど
What? Isn't shogi a game for old men?
（女子生徒Ｄ）何それ？
将棋って—
おじいちゃんが
やるもんじゃないの？
Shogi? Game? At home?
（女子生徒Ｅ）
将棋ゲーム？ 家で？ おたく？
Is he a nerd?
Is that why he's repeating?
Because he ditched so much school?
（女子生徒Ｆ）それでダブったの？
学校サボって？
Oh, is that what happened?
（女子生徒Ｇ）へぇ〜 そうなんだ
I-I'm getting out of here.
で… 出ようっと
When the classes changed,
my classmates immediately formed groups.
（零）クラスの子たちは—
クラス替えが済んだ瞬間に
グループになっていて—
How is a loser with no courage or skills to do so like me supposed to join them now?
そして もう既に
出来上がってしまったその中に—
飛び込む勇気も スキルも
持ち合わせてないダメな僕は—
一体 どうしたら…
（零）よっ 入れてくんない？
Hey, mind if I sit with you?
Like that?
（零）こんな感じか？
No, no. More normal, and less eager.
いやいや もっと普通に気負わず…
（零）ねぇ 一緒に
食べてもいいかな？
Hey, would it be okay if I ate with you?
（零）こんな感じにサラッと…
Just like that, smoothly...
なんて 普通に出来てりゃ—
I mean, if I could do that,
I wouldn't be eating lunch by myself for 11 years running!
11年 １人で昼飯食ってねぇよ！
Nope. It's impossible.
ダメ… 無理… かむ…
絶対 かむ自信がある あぁ…
I'll definitely stumble on the words.
Well, this is what I imagined would happen.
まあ 想定はしてたことだ
I just have to bear it alone quietly.
また 粛々と
１人で過ごしてけばいいだけだ
2 Years
あと２年…
たったあと２年ぽっちだ
Two more years.
730 Days
17,520 hours
Just two more years of being alone.
1,051,200 Minutes
63,072,000 Seconds
そんなことより—
More importantly,
the class-promotion tournament starts in June,
今は６月から始まる順位戦と
目の前の新人戦に集中だ
and I need to focus on my upcoming matches in the Rookie Tournament.
Shogi
Hall
For the class-promotion tournament,
順位戦
僕のいるＣ１クラスは 総勢34名
there are 34 players in Class C1 including me.
その中で １年をかけて—
From among them, ten matches are arranged by lottery.
抽選で組み合わせが決められた
10局を戦い—
Only the top two players are then promoted to B2.
トップの２人だけが
Ｂ２へと昇級を決める
Nikaidou's name wasn't listed on the schedule of matches.
その対戦予定表の中に
二海堂の名はなく…
What is the meaning of this, Kiriyama?!
（二海堂晴信）
どういうことだ 桐山！
知らないよ！
Don't ask me!
（二海堂）お前 今 千駄ヶ谷(せんだがや)？
俺 今から行く！ 待ってろ！
Are you in Sendagaya now? I'm on my way! Wait for me!
Sendagaya
Shogi Hall
So now we'll just have to clash in the Rookie Tournament.
こうなったら
新人戦で当たるしかないな
おしいことに俺とお前は—
It's too bad that you're in the
A block while I'm in the B block,
Ａブロック Ｂブロックに
分かれてしまったが—
そんなの 決勝まで
勝ち残ればいいだけのこと！
but we'll just have to keep winning so we can meet in the finals!
B block
A block
Nikaidou
Kiriyama
Here->
Wait a second! Did you just say the finals?!
ちょまっ
今 決勝までって言った？
Give me a break!
おい！ こら！
ざっくり判断にも 程がある！
There are limits in making snap decisions too!
I'm just speaking the truth!
俺は真実を言ってるだけだ！
（零）あっ あ…
（二海堂）ひるむな桐山！
Don't falter, Kiriyama!
Our legend...
２人の伝説は—
is only beginning.
まだ 始まったばかりだぜ
L-L-Legend?
で で… 伝説？
And why is it "ours"?!
というか ２人のって何？
Jiggle
（零）あっ う う…
よろしくね〜
Y-Yep. Looking forward to it.
Yeah. I'll have to do my best.
そうだ 頑張ろう
Because that's all I can do for both
新人戦も順位戦も—
the Rookie Tournament and the class-promotion tournament.
今の僕に出来ることは
それだけなのだから…
（林田(はやしだ)高志(たかし)）うーん あっ？
（零）頑張ろう…
また いちから ひとつひとつ
I'll do my best.
Starting from square one, one move at a time...
One move at a time...
ひとつひとつ…
Hey, Kiriyama!
おーい 桐山！
Hold it right there!
（林田）待て こらー！
（零）えー！
き〜り〜や〜ま〜　てめぇ
Kiriyama, you bastard...
（零）な な… 先生？
何してんすか
Wh-What... Mr. Hayashida? What are you doing?
You shouldn't just abandon the students you were with.
生徒さん ほったらかしちゃ
ダメじゃないですか
I don't give a shit!
何でもくそもあるか！
生徒にそんな顔されたら
どうすりゃいいっつうのさ〜
What else am I supposed to do when I see a student make that face?!
I have to run after him!
走ってくるしかないだろうさ！
フンッ
こんちくしょー！
Dammit!
A-A face like "that"? A-A face like what?
そ… そんな顔って
ど… どんな顔？
A face like this! Like this!
Tousle
（林田）こういう顔だよ こういう
（零）ギャー
Tousle
So, um...
（零）で あの…
（林田）ん？ ああ？
Huh? What?
Is it okay for you to have lunch with me,
even though you're not my teacher this year?
（零）いいんですか？
前の学年の担任が
今年も去年の生徒とごはん食べて…
（林田）ああ 大丈夫
It's fine.
I just saw the gloomy look on the face of my former introverted student
とある事情を抱えて
出席日数ぎりぎりだった—
who barely passed the attendance requirement due to "certain circumstances."
心を閉ざし気味の生徒の
曇りがちな表情が気になって…
って言ったら—
When I told them that, they said,
"Mr. Hayashida, hurry up and go to him!"
“先生 早く行ってあげて”って
言われたぞ
Why would you casually make me sound
like a loser while you get to play the hero?
何 さりげなく僕の株を
下げることによって—
まんまと自分の株を
上げてんですか！
It's because I want to be invited to the students' Christmas party this year.
今年こそ クリスマス会に
呼ばれる教師になりたいからな
I'm desperate too.
先生だって 必死なんだ
But still,
でもさあ 桐山 お前—
why did you come back here, Kiriyama?
なんでまた
ここに来ちゃってるの？
It's the first term of a new school year.
新学年の新学期
今がまさにハンターチャンス
This is your chance.
If you don't make an effort now, when would you?
今 頑張んないでどうすんの？
…って 頑張ってるよな
But you are making an effort, right?
だから先生—
That's why I can't tell you to
"do your best" any more than this.
お前にこれ以上
頑張れ！ なんて言えねぇよ
So I had an idea.
で 先生 考えた
Let's make a shogi club.
将棋部を作ろう
し… 将棋部？
Sh-Shogi club?
Wait...
And I'll be the adviser.
（林田）…したら 俺は顧問になる
Then it wouldn't be strange for me to look after you.
そんならお前をかまっても
おかしくないよな？
After all, I'd be your adviser.
だって 顧問だもん
That might be easy to say, but...
（零）いや…
でも そんな簡単に…
（林田）５人集めて
顧問がいりゃあ 部は作れる
With five members and an adviser, you can make a club.
Yeah, but still...
（零）いやっ でも…
We just need to find four more members.
（林田）あと４人 探しゃあいい
Find? Find how?
（零）探すったって…
でも どうやって？
Don't sweat the details.
（林田）とにかく探してみようぜ
But I don't think we can find them so easily...
でも そんな簡単には見つからない
（零）あっ
（林田）でも… が何だって？
Just remembered
something
But what, exactly?
Stare
Oh, uh, it's nothing!
（零）あー いえ
何でもありません
（林田）なあ 桐山
Hey, Kiriyama.
お前は何で もう一度—
Why did you want to take another
shot at being a high school student?
高校生をやり直そうって
思ったんだ？
Was it to eat lunch alone on the stairs like this?
こんなふうに
１人で階段で飯を食うためか？
Of course not, right, Kiriyama?
違うだろ？ 桐山…
（零）はい
Right.
（零）これで
逃げてないことになるのかな
"Will this make it seem like I'm not running away?"
"What if I'm only pretending not to run away?"
（零）逃げてないふりだったら
どうしよう…
The truth is,
本当はずっと…
ずっと心にのしかかってた
it's always weighed heavily on my mind.
そして 本当は気付いていた
And I'd realized it too.
このまんまじゃ もっともっと
苦しくなるだろうってこと
At this rate, things would only become more painful for me.
That's when it hit me.
あのとき 思ったんだ
あんなふうに 身ひとつで—
If only I could blend in so well like he was,
みんなの中に溶け込めたら—
just how... how very...
どんなに… どんなに
どんなに
うれしいだろうって…
how very happy could I be?
（零）先生 将棋部の顧問
お願いできますか？
Mr. Hayashida. Can I ask you to be the shogi club's adviser?
Sure thing.
（林田）おうよ
And Kiriyama, of course, you know...
…で 桐山
もちろん あれだろう？
You'll coach me too, right?
俺にも指導してくれるんだろ？
Huh? Oh, yes. Of course.
（零）え？ あぁ…
はい もちろん
Yes! There it is!
イエス！ 来たこれ〜
I get a pro's coaching for free!
ただでプロの指導 イエス！
I want to get beyond the wall of amateur 4-dan!
俺っ 俺 アマ４段の壁を
越えたいんだよ
There's this jerk I want to beat on Net Shogi 24!
ネット将棋24で にくいやつがいて
勝ちたいんだよ〜
Mr. Hayashida, just a minute ago, I was moved by your kindness...
先生 感動したのに…
優しさに…
Faculty Office
Ahhh...
N-Nobody. Nobody wants to join.
（林田）い… いねぇ…
入部希望ゼロって…
What? Is shogi really so minor?
何？ 将棋って
そんなにマイナーなの？
Everyone's like, "Shogi? Sorry, I'm not really interested."
（林田）みんな
“将棋？ すみません”
（林田）“あんまり興味が”って
どういうこと？！
What's up with that?
Even though I love it so much...
俺 こんなに将棋 大好きなのに…
Sorry.
（零）すいません…
There's nothing for you to apologize about.
（林田）いや
お前が謝るこっちゃねぇだろう
（零）いえ… 何となく…
I kind of feel responsible...
そうだ！
That's it!
After School Bunsen Burners Club
Noguchi!
（林田）野口(のぐち)！
（部員たち）ん？
Waft
It stinks in here again!
*High school
third-year
（林田）またしても 臭っ！
Mr. Hayashida, long time no see.
（野口英作(えいさく)）おっ 林田先生
お久しぶりですな
Wh-What are you guys doing this time?
（林田）な な 何してんの
お前たち また？
Packed
（野口）ハハハッ
見てのとおり 納豆の収穫ですよ
Packed
As you can see, we're harvesting natto.
Sticky
Packed
*High school
third-year
いや〜 だから
どうして学校で納豆を？
Okay, but why "harvest" natto at school?
ハハハッ
それはこうやって—
What we do is wrap steamed soybeans in a straw of rice and let it sit for a day at about 40 degrees,
まず 蒸した大豆を
稲のわらで包み—
40度くらいに保温して
１日置きますと—
わらに付着している枯草菌(こそうきん)
バチルス･サブティリスが—
which allows the bacillus subtilis in
the straw to spread to the soybeans,
大豆に移行し増殖することによって
発酵が起こり…
and through this proliferation, fermentation occurs.
Y-Yeah. I didn't actually ask "how" you're doing it.
どうやってってのを
聞いたわけではなくってね
Wow, this really is natto!
わーっ
本当に納豆ですね〜
Sticky
Got offered some
Hey, you're eating it already?
おい そこ
もう 食ってるし
Once in a while, you don't hold back.
お前 ところどころ素直なんだよな
Anyway, where'd you get the straw of rice from?
つーか この わらとか
どっから持ってきたのさ
ハハハッ よい質問ですな
*High school
third-year
Excellent question.
by Noguchi Eisaku
Is Self-sufficiency Possible
at a High School?
by Noguchi Eisaku
Is Self-sufficiency Possible
at a High School?
by Noguchi Eisaku
Is Self-sufficiency Possible
at a High School?
by Noguchi Eisaku
Is Self-sufficiency Possible
at a High School?
by Noguchi Eisaku
I did it for my thesis here.
この論文の執筆のために—
I harvested it while growing rice on the school roof last year.
昨年 屋上で稲作をとり行った際に
収穫されたものでしてな
Wait a second!
（林田）ちょっと待って
What's that thesis?
その論文 何？
つーか 何のためよ
Who are you presenting it to?
I mean, what's it for?
誰に提出するの？
And you can't practice self-sufficiency at school!
つーか 学校で
自給自足しちゃダメでしょ
I don't even know where to begin.
もう
どっからつっこんだらいいのか…
No, wait!
って いけねっ！
I almost forgot my original purpose.
本題を忘れてた〜
That's right!
そうだった！
Thud!
野口 お前 将棋できねぇ？
Noguchi, do you know how to play shogi?
Shogi...
（野口）将棋…
My grandfather taught me to play it when I was young.
幼少の頃
祖父に習った程度ですが—
But indeed, that is a deep game, isn't it?
いやはや
あれは奥の深いゲームですな
Yes!
（林田）やった！
So listen, we're trying to put together a shogi club,
but we're having a hard time getting the five members.
はぁ いや 今さ
将棋部作ろうと思ってんだけど—
全然 ５人集まんなくってさ
But now we've finally got someone!
やっと１人いた！
ハハハッ
いずこも同じですな
We're in the same boat.
我が 放科部も 今や
存続の危機にさらされていましてな
The continued existence of my Afterburners Club is in peril.
At this rate, the club may be disbanded at the club budget meeting in May.
このままでは
５月の部の予算会議で—
廃部にされるかもしれないのです
What?
え？ 何？ 部員いっぱいいたじゃん
どうしたの？
But you had a lot of members. What happened?
先輩たちは 皆 卒業なさいました
The upperclassmen all graduated.
Hold on.
（林田）ちょっと待って
あの人たち 先輩だったの？
Those members were all older than you?!
Two Years Ago
Is this the Science Club?
科学部はこちらですかな？
*High school
first-year
Sir?!
*Upperclassmen
（先輩Ａ）先輩？
（先輩Ｂ）いや 部長！
No, President!
Yay
Wow
*High school
first-year
*Upperclassmen
Wow
Yay
Yes, they were marvelous mentors.
（野口）はい 良い先輩たちでした
Yay
Wow
入部したその日から—
From the day I joined the club,
even though I was a first-year, they called me "sir."
１年の私のことを
先輩と呼んでくださって…
Bam!
I wanted to keep the club going and pass on the wonder of science to younger students,
何とか 部を存続させ—
若い人たちに科学のすばらしさを
伝えたかったのですが—
たった４人になってしまっては
それももう なすすべもなく—
but with only four members left, it's all over.
Is Self-sufficiency Possible
at a High School?
by Noguchi Eisaku
If I could only complete this thesis...
この論文さえ完成していれば…
Even if you did finish,
I don't know if it would pass on the joy of science.
あっ いやあ してても
科学の良さは伝わるかどうか…
（部員たち）は〜あ
Wait a second.
ちょっと待てよ
That's it!
そうだよ　お前たちさ—
Why don't you guys combine to form one club?
もういっそ
１個の部にしちまえば？
One
member
Four
members
Total - 5 People
Yes!
イエスッ！
That makes sense!
なるほど！
All right! Then without further ado, how about we play a match?
よーし じゃあ 早速だけど
ちょっと 指してみねえ？
I've kind of been holding back, but from now on,
I can play a lot of matches with Kiriyama!
今まで何となく遠慮してたけど—
これからは桐山と
目いっぱい指せるぞ〜
After all, I'm the adviser.
だって俺 顧問だし〜
ぐっふふふ…
Um, Noguchi. I feel like I should apologize for imposing on you every time...
あの… 野口さん
何か すみません
いつも
迷惑ばかりかけてしまって…
I'm actually kind of excited about this.
何か ワクワクしますな〜
祖父が亡くなってから—
After my grandfather passed away,
I wasn't able to find anyone to play with.
ずっと 指せる相手が
見つからなかったんです
フッフフフ
I'm still just a novice, but will you teach me too, Kiriyama?
初心者でお恥ずかしいですが—
私にも教えていただけますか？
桐山君
Yes, of course.
はい もちろん…
Of course I will.
もちろんです
After School Bunsen Burners Club
And so, the Afterburners Club became the After School Shogi Science Club.
（零）という訳で
放課後理科クラブ改め—
After School Bunsen Burners Club
放課後将棋科学部
略して 将科部結成と相成り
After School Bunsen Burners Club
Or for short, the Sho-sci Club.
After School Shogi Science Club
A club. A club, huh?
（零）部活… 部活かあ
And a shogi club at that.
しかも将棋の… おぉ
See? Like I said.
なっ 言ったろ
（零）帰り道 先生は—
On the way home...
In my experience, I've found that it's easier to do something than worry about it.
案ずるより産むが易しって
俺の経験上だと—
Or that's about 80% right, anyway.
８割方 真実なんだよな
...he said that with a grin.
（零）って言って ニヤッと笑った
New School Year
Fighter
The seat next to me is always empty.
（零）僕の隣は いつも空席だ
What? I have to sit next to Kiriyama?
（金田(かねだ)）ええ？！ 隣 桐山？
うっそ ぜってぇ 嫌だ
No way! Forget that!
Excuse me, sir? Sir! Sir!
はい 先生
先生 先生！
Can I change seats?
席… 席 変わっていいですか？
Knock it off, Kaneda. Don't be stubborn.
（先生）こらっ 金田
勝手言うな！
Oh, come on, please?
ねえねえ いいでしょう？
Kaneda, just hurry up and sit down.
（生徒Ａ）金田君
早く座りなよ〜 もう
席 空いてんじゃん
先生 いいでしょう？
There are other open seats. It's fine, right?
Fine, do what you want!
あー もう好きにしろ！
Yeah!
やりーっ へへへ…
Okay, class 4-E is leaving!
（添乗員）はーい
４年５組 出発しまーす
Hey, hurry up and sit down!
（先生）こーら 早く座れ！
I have the same thoughts whenever this happens.
（零）こういうとき いつも思う
嫌なら嫌で構わないから
もう少し静かに—
If you don't want to sit by me, that's fine.
I'm lucky the seat next to you was open.
But could you be a little quieter about it and not make a scene?
目立たないように
やってくれないかなって
Kaneda's so annoying.
Yeah, he's always like this.
でも バスが動きだして
少し ほっとした
But once the bus pulled out, I always felt a little relieved.
After all,
（零）だって ずっと隣で
ずっと嫌そうにされるより—
it was much, much easier this way
than to sit next to someone who hates me.
ずっとずっと 気が楽だ…
Okay. We're going to have lunch now.
はい
それじゃあ ここでお弁当です
After you're done, go to the bathroom,
and be back at the bus by 1:30.
１時半までにトイレなど済ませて
バスに戻ること
Okay!
（生徒たち）はーい
All right, then you're on your own.
はい じゃあ 自由行動で—
Dismissed!
解散！
Shoot.
（零）参った…
どうしたらいいんだ これ
What am I supposed to do here?
The field is huge!
原っぱ ひろ〜
エスケープゾーン全くなし？
There's no escape zone at all.
こんな だだっぴろい所で
１人で弁当とか—
Eating my lunch all alone in a wide open field like this will make me stand out so much that I'll die.
もう 目立ちすぎて死ねる…
And worse, if the teacher finds me...
その上 先生に見つかったら…
（先生）こーら 桐山
何 １人で食ってんだ
Hey, Kiriyama.
Why are you eating alone?
That's no good.
Whap
Why do you
exclude Kiriyama?
（零）来週のホームルームの
話題にされるのは…
I'll inevitably become the focus of
next week's homeroom assignment!
Today's topic: Why do you exclude Kiriyama?
Think about this seriously, everyone!
（先生）真面目に考えろよ
Huh?
（生徒Ｂ）えー
（生徒Ｃ）何それー？
What the heck is that?
That would be the worst.
最悪だ
Squeak
It's tough enough just having everyone hate me.
みんなに嫌われてるだけでも
つらいのに—
Squeak
To be put on display on top of that wouldn't solve anything.
その上 さらし者にされて しかも
解決なんてするわけなくて—
Squeak
It would only bring attention to the fact that I'm despised.
嫌われてるって事実が 更に
浮き彫りになるだけっていうか…
Squeak
うん　もう絶対に避けたい！
I want to avoid that no matter what!
うん ちょっと遠いけど
あそこまで行こう
It's a little far, but I'll go over there.
It'll be okay.
大丈夫…
This'll work.
Quietly, and don't jog over.
こそこそ小走りにならず—
If I just walk over slowly, like normal, I won't stand out.
堂々と ゆっくり歩けば目立たない
Normally, normally...
普通に 普通に…
Yes!
（零）よし 着いた
I made it!
It's cold!
うっ 冷たっ！
And damp.
湿ってる
あっ そうだ
クリアファイル敷けば 大丈夫か
I know! It'll be fine if I put down my clear file folder.
There's a lot of ants!
うわぁ アリいっぱい！
ああ… お弁当に登らないで
Please don't crawl on my lunch!
あっ そうだ
I've got it.
Yeah.
There you go.
Come to think of it, how do ants carry away candy?
（零）そういえば アリは
あめをどうやって運ぶんだろう？
I guess they lick it, melting tiny pieces at a time to carry off?
少しずつ なめて溶かして
運ぶんだろうか…
With their little mouths...
あの小さな口で…
I made a copy of this from Dad's book.
お父さんの本から
写させてもらった 117手詰め
Checkmate in 117 moves...
You solved it?
（幸田(こうだ)柾近(まさちか)）おう〜 解けたのか？
85手詰めが…
The 85 moves one?
すごいぞ 零
That's incredible, Rei!
I couldn't solve that one until I was in junior high.
俺がそれを解けたのは
中学に入ってからだったぞ
My adoptive father is a shogi player.
（零）僕を引き取ってくれた父は
棋士だった
He turned pro at age 19.
19歳でプロになったという…
I wonder if Dad will be happy
（零）もし僕が
この問題を解けたら—
if I solve this problem too.
父は また喜んでくれるだろうか
（笛の音）
（先生）集合！ 走れ！
Gather 'round! Run!
What?! It's 1:30 already?!
あっ え？ もう１時半？
Yikes! I haven't cleaned up!
あっ やばっ 片付けてない！
Um, uh, have I forgotten anything? Um...
えーと えーと
忘れ物は えーと…
H-Huh?
あっ あれ？
The candy! It's that small already?!
あめ！ もうあんな小さい！
Amazing!
すごい！
I had no idea.
（零）知らなかった…
ありって あんな小さいのに—
Despite being so little,
ants can dissolve candy at an incredible speed.
ものすごい早さで
あめを溶かすんだ
Hey, Kiriyama!
おーい 桐山
You're late! Where were you?
遅いぞ　どこ行ってたんだ？
Sorry!
（零）すみません
Um, the bathroom was crowded...
えーと　トイレが混んでて…
We'll be leaving.
出発しまーす
Is there anyone whose seat neighbor hasn't come back yet?
隣の人が
戻ってきてないやつ いるか？
No!
（生徒たち）はーい
大丈夫でーす！
Huh? Kiriyama, where's your seat neighbor?
あれ？ 桐山 隣は？
It's okay. There was no one here from the start.
あっ 大丈夫です
最初からいません
Oh yeah.
あ そっか
Then we're all here, huh?
よし じゃあ そろったな
出発するぞ
Let's go!
Okay!
（生徒たち）
はーい うえーい
"There was no one here from the start."
（零）最初からいません…
The moment I answered, I felt a lump in my throat.
とっさにそう答えた瞬間
胸が詰まった
I wanted to ask him if the seat next to me would be empty for the rest of my life.
先生 僕の隣は—
このまま一生
空席なんでしょうか？
All right. Next, seat 5. The match with Sugawara.
（職員）はい 次は５番の席
菅原君と対局です
（零）そんな僕にとって
それは 魔法の切符だった
To me, that was a magic ticket.
Good luck.
（零･菅原）お願いします
As long as I had that ticket,
（零）その切符さえあれば—
誰かが必ず—
somebody would always,
自動的に—
automatically,
sit across from me.
目の前に座ってくれるのだ
I encountered many different kinds of people.
出会う人には いろんな人がいた
Crap! Who is this little brat?!
（おじさん）かーっ！
何だよ このクソガキ！
You're too good! Sheesh!
強すぎんだろ おい！
ふん ちきしょう！
Dammit. I'll walk with you to the station,
since it's already dark.
駅まで送ってってやる
もう暗いからな
Here, drink this.
飲め！ ほらっ
Do you like hot chocolate? Dammit!
ココア好きか？ こんちきしょう
Th-Thank you.
あっ ありがとうございます
（おじさん）へへっ
（零）優しい人も… もちろん…
Some were kind.
And of course...
Well, you're pretty bad.
（青年）何だ 弱いじゃん
幸田先生のとこに—
Even though I heard Mr. Kouda took you in as his disciple.
内弟子に入ったやつだって
聞いてたけど…
...some didn't like me.
（零）僕を嫌う人も…
でも 戦い続けている間は
絶対に誰かが 前に座ってくれた
But as long as I kept fighting,
somebody would always sit before me.
これは切符だ
"This is a ticket."
この切符を握っている間は—
As long as I have this ticket,
僕には居場所がある
I belong somewhere.
This ticket was my lifeline.
この切符が 僕の命綱だった
どこにも
たどりつけなくてもいい…
I didn't have to arrive anywhere.
I could just keep on riding.
乗り続けていられる…
ただ それだけでもいい…
That was fine with me.
If I got off this train, I'd have nowhere to go.
この列車を降りたら
もう僕には 居る場所がない
This ticket alone would take me to tomorrow.
この切符だけが
僕を明日へ運んでくれる
I had to hold on to this ticket like my life depended on it.
これだけは 死んでも
離すわけにはいかなかった…
守り抜かなくては…
I have to protect it...
at all costs.
何に代えてでも…
（二海堂）桐山 桐山 桐山…
おい 桐山…
Kiriyama. Kiriyama. Kiriyama!
Hey, Kiriyama!
Kiriyama!
（二海堂）桐山！
（零）あっ
What are you spacing out for?
何 ぼーっとしてんだ
Sit your butt down!
早く座れ！
He went on the attack, and it was amazing!
動いたんだ すげーぞ！
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）うーん
（松本(まつもと)一砂(いっさ)）おおおーっ！
（二海堂）５三歩(ふ)成りの
成り捨てが好手なんだよ！
Playing P-5c+ as a sacrifice was a great move!
If Gx5c and R-7g follow, what's next?
（二海堂）同金(きん)に
７七飛(ひ)でどうする？
Kiriyama, what do you think?
（二海堂）桐山 お前 どう見る？
How much time is left?
残り時間は？
Shogi Dragon Fujimoto has eight minutes.
藤本棋竜が８分
兄者(あにじゃ)は もう３分切ってる
Big Brother has less than three minutes.
（零）７七飛に対して
飛車の頭をたたいて
Regarding the R-7g play,
crush it by dropping a pawn right in front.
Then take the initiative by doing G-6d.
６四金と出て
先手を取って受ける
G-6d? Not P*7c?
６四金？
７三歩じゃなくて？
If you did that, B*6b would put you in a tough spot.
（零）それだと ６二角(かく)が厳しい
It's not like I've changed.
（零）僕が変わったわけではない
そして—
Also,
the people around me haven't changed either.
周りが変わってくれたわけでもない
ただ 気が遠くなりそうな
日々を—
It's just that while desperately playing and playing
every single day until it seemed like my head would spin,
必死で指して 指して…
ただ 指し続けているうちに…
one day, I realized that other people were traveling with me toward the same place,
ある日ふと—
同じ光のさす方へ
向かう人たちと—
where the light was shining.
一緒に旅をしていることに気付いた
Like a resplendent meteor shower
（零）そして 今日も—
And today too,
Your words enter my ears and catch fire
someone is sitting across from me.
目の前に座る人がいて—
They come together like a school of fish
And form a warm corner in my once chilly bosom
Another new story will begin.
またひとつ
新しい物語が始まる
As I stood in place, not knowing the right way to reach out
Our journey toward the shining light will continue.
光のさす方へ
僕らの旅は 続くのだ
Your hand reached out to touch mine
And no matter how many nights may pass
That warmth still lingers and pulses within
Fighter
Your very presence shines a bright light on every part of my life
Your racing heartbeat resonates with my frozen heart and sets it ablaze
Before long, the fire dies out
Leaving just one smoldering ember
Which remains with me and won't ever go away
Living inside of me in a place closest to my heart
Illustration: Hagio Moto
（零）３月のライオン
Thank you for watching
"March comes in like a lion."
御覧いただき
ありがとうございました